Nader Esmael

Moreno Valley, CA 92555 | 951-288-8825 | ncesmael@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/ncesmael/ | laternader.github.io/

Professional Summary

Enthusiastic data analyst with strong Python, SQL, Excel, and data visualization skills. With over four years of experience researching companies for business development, strategizing in mergers and acquisitions, and managing databases, I have developed my analytical, quantitative, and precise communication skills.

Skills

Most Experience: Python(Numpy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Matplotlib, Seaborn), SQL(PostgreSQL, MYSQL), Advance Office & Excel **Familiar With:** Github, HTML, R (ggplot2)

Intermediate Experience: Tableau (Creating Dashboards), Web Scraping, Statistical Modeling, Git Control, ETL **Soft Skills:** Customer Facing Experience, Adaptability, Ability to Explain Data Topics to Non-technical Audiences, Worked Cross Functionally, Problem Framing, Data Collection, Precise Communication, Time Management, Presentation Skills, Reporting

Projects

Reci-Please | Hackathon/Group Project

November 2021

- Worked alongside UX/UI designers, software engineers, and data scientists to create a elderly, user-friendly web-application to find recipes based on filter algorithms and recommendation models
- Extracted, cleaned, and transformed over 500,000 recipes scraped from Food.com
- Provided data perspective to assist in navigation of the app based on user preferences to locate recipes

Depression or Shower Thoughts: That is the question? | Solo Concept Project

October 2020

- Pulled 20,000 Reddit posts using Pushift API and designed an NLP-based Random Forest classifier that differentiates if a
 post is a random thought or exhibits signs of depression
- Investigated r/depression and r/showerthoughts subreddits to understand the connection between language and behavior, focusing on its significance in detecting signs of depression
- Utilized the model's coefficient to determine commonly ignored keywords that lead to the misclassification of depression and achieve error margins as low as 9%

Professional Experience

Data Analyst, Freelance, Moreno Valley, CA

January 2021 - present

- Tutored high school students in Python coding techniques and assisted in completing homework assignments
- Investigated and resolved inventory related issues such as reduction of excess and created opportunities for increasing sales and social media presence for a local anime stickers & product vendor

Front Desk Associate, Massage Envy, Moreno Valley, CA

March 2021 - August 2021

- Created a welcoming environment and identified opportunities to drive merchandise, increase customer satisfaction, and provide solutions
- Implemented a modality sheet, reference guidelines, and manual for current and future Front Desk Associates through Google Docs and Sheets to organize therapists' preferences and schedules, accounting for client needs

Mergers & Acquisitions Research Analyst, Harvey & Company LLC, Newport Beach, CA

March 2019 - January 2020

- Increased top-line revenue 150% by developing strategic search queries and research tactics for over 10 platforms
- Performed market research and due diligence to identify targets for acquisition based on market conditions, competitor research, industry standards
- Successfully influenced and managed resources across various workgroups and functions including assisting other analysts and interns with research development
- Designed detailed marketing materials and finance reports for bi-weekly meetings with executives and management teams to discuss research efforts and other applicable information

Conference & Events Student Assistant, Cal Poly Pomona Associated Student, Inc., Pomona, CA August 2017 – August 2018

- Supervised and trained six other team members including safety training, operation protocols, and time management
- Supported senior leadership through identifying process improvements and positioning the business for growth potential
- Performed assessments and benchmarks of programs to improve schedules, delegation, and coordination

Education

General Assembly, Data Science Immersive Program

December 2020

California State Polytechnic, University (Pomona), B.S. Applied Mathematics & Statistics

June 2018

Leadership: President & Founder of Sportsfest Club (2016-17), Athletics Chair of Barkada (2016-17), Internal Affairs Director of PASK (2015-2016)

Additional Courses: Data Science Nanodegree (June 2020), Completed SQL Bootcamp, Datafest - High Ranking Participant (2018), Dataquest.io Data Analyst/Data Scientist courses in Python and SQL